Joseph J. Menditto Papers VHP2004/12
CCSU Veterans History Project
Joseph J. Menditto Papers
Bulk, 1942-1945
1942-1945, 1998, 2004
VHP2004/12
CCSU Veterans History Project
98.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Menditto, Joseph J., 1920 -
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph J. Menditto was drafted into the U.S. Army in 1942 and was sent to Camp Gruber in Oklahoma for basic training. There he had military intelligence training, learning how to operate observation posts for the front lines. His battalion shipped out in October of 1943 for North Africa in a convoy of 105 ships. The large number of ships helped to defer the possibility of being torpedoed by German submarines. Menditto's company remained in North Africa for 4 months before sailing to Italy to back up forces there. There Menditto, fought in the Battle of Monte Cassino, and witnessed a friend from New Britain sustain injuries that led to the amputation of both his legs. Menditto describes the procedure followed by the radio man, in particular the procedures they followed during the Battle for Santa Maria Infante. Menditto also describes his experiences in Angio, Italy, where it was his unit's job to cut off the use of the road to the German soldiers who were using it to receive supplies. It was also at this time that the U.S. soldiers ran low on supplies and became desperate for food at times. He describes the hard conditions that the soldiers were met with. It was in Mount Capello, Italy, that Meditto was injured not once but twice. After healing in a hospital in Rome, he was sent back to the front in Bologna, which was attacked just before the end of the war was announced. After volunteering to help return German POW's to Munich, Menditto was shipped to the United States where he was discharged at Fort Bragg. Menditto returned to New Britain, and joined the VFW, the American Legion, and the Elks. He remained in touch with many of his unit members through yearly reunions. Menditto's experiences during the Battle of Monte Cassino were also documented in the book "Monte Cassino: the Hardest Fought Battle of World War II" by Matthew Parker.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into 4 series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Military documents
Series III, Publications
Series IV, Multi-media
United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 351th.; Africa, North; Camp Gruber (Okla.); Cassino, Battle of, Cassino, Italy, 1944; Italy; World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Italy; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military intelligence
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - V–Mail from Menditto to his parents while serving overseas, October 16, 1944; 2004/12.I.1
  - V-Mail from Menditto to his wife while serving overseas, May 22 - October 24, 1945; 2004/12.I.2; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Joseph Menditto’s letter to his fellow veterans, April 12, 2004; 2004-12.I.3; 3.0 Digital objects
- Series II: Military Documents
  - A list of Veterans transferred from active duty to the Enlisted Reserve Corps, November 21, 1944; VHP2004/12.II.1
  - A letter to Menditto’s mother informing of his progress after an injury during Battle., November 2, 1944; VHP2004/12.II.2
  - A follow-up letter to Menditto’s mother. Giving an update on his progress following an injury during battle, November 14, 1944; VHP2004/12.II.3
  - A letter informing Menditto’s mother of his return to duty following an injury during battle, December 2, 1944; VHP2004/12.II.4
  - Transportation Request Document, September 6, 1945; VHP2004/12.II.5
  - Honorable Discharge, 1945; VHP2004/12.II.6
  - Honorable Discharge Certificate, October 23, 1945; VHP2004/12.II.7
  - Separation Qualification Record, 1945; VHP2004/12.II.8
  - Citation to the 2nd Battalion, 351st Infantry Regiment For meritorious service near Mt. Cappello, Italy, June 11, 1946; VHP2004/12.II.9
  - Menditto’s Bronze Star Medal Certificate For outstanding service during WW II, January 13, 1992; VHP2004/12.II.10
  - Authorization For Issuance of Awards, January 13, 1992; VHP2004/12.II.11
  - Menditto’s list of medals received, Circa 1992; VHP2004/12.II.12
  - Letter from Senator Joseph Lieberman, July 29, 1998; VHP2004/12.II.13
- Series III: Publications
  - Excerpt of the book "Road to Rome", n.d.; VHP2004/12.III.1; 33.0 Digital objects
  - Joseph Menditto biography from the book "88th Infantry Division 'Blue Devils'", VHP2004/12.III.2; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Excerpt of the book "Monte Cassino: The Hardest-Fought Battle of World War II" by Matthew Parker, June 1, 2004; VHP2004/12.III.3; 5.0 Digital objects
  - Excerpt of the book "Small Unit Actions" published by Historical Division, US War Department, n.d.; VHP2004/12.III.4; 34.0 Digital objects
- Series IV: Multi-Media
  - Oral history interview with Joseph J. Menditto, August 26, 2004; VHP2004/12.IV.1; 1.0 dvd (Disk DVD VHP2004/12 #1, Box VHP Interview 1)
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    Interview video also available online.
    Streaming Video